Finding Aid for the Philippine Zines Collection LSC.2281
UCLA Library Special Collections
Philippine zines collection
2006-2017
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2281
4 linear feet (10 boxes)
The Philippine zines reflects the feelings, aesthetics, and cultural and political ideologies of various individuals and artist collectives from the Philippines. The zine's content mostly includes creative works, such as comics, illustrations, poetry, and short stories to reflect topics, such as mental health, interpersonal relationships, culture, political climate, and more. The Philippine zines spans the years of 2006-2017, with the bulk of the material from 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All zines have been purchased through zine fairs and a seller based in the Philippines by Jade Alburo, Librarian for Southeast Asian Studies, Pacific Islands Studies, and Religion at UCLA Library.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9977285753606533
Biographical / Historical
In the 1980s, Philippine zine culture first emerged, as a result of music fan zines that were introduced at the same time punk music was being introduced in the country. Contemporarily, the content of the zines Filpinos produce have expanded to explore different themes such as personal, political, cultural, literary, art, feminism, and more. The zine culture flourished in the 2000s due to the emergence of the digital age that allowed artists to post their zines on different platforms. Zine culture, however, was catalyzed by the emergence of a small press conference called Better Living Through Xeroxography (BLTX). This press conference was founded on empowering artists through the highlighting of problems in mainstream publishing and introducing self-publication as a solution. BLTX was able take the discontent over mainstream publishing and push for a way to educate and mobilize to address it through artistic means.
Scope and Content
The Philippine zines reflects the feelings, aesthetics, and cultural and political ideologies of various individuals and artist collectives from the Philippines. The zine's content mostly includes creative works, such as comics, illustrations, poetry, and short stories to reflect topics, such as mental health, interpersonal relationships, culture, political climate, and more. The Philippine zines spans the years of 2006-2017, with the bulk of the material from 2017.
The collection features zines from various individuals or collaborators who circulate their creations in small press expos, like Better Living Through Xeroxography (BLTX), or through local collectives, like Magpies Press, Saturnino Basilla Studio, and Soup Zine Library. Many of the zines from this collection are also a product from local universities' organizations or clubs, where students have collaborated to publish and print their work together.
Arrangement
The collection has been intellectually arranged by title.
Zines; Politics and culture -- Philippines
- [untitled], 2013; Busamante, Chubbs A.; Ligot, Kabel Mishka; Cadiz, Marianne (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This untitled zine consists of collages of maps and pictures of the San Francisco Bay Area. It also includes a short poem and an extracted explanation about plate tectonics, which the author uses as a metaphor of the constantly changing relationships in our own lives. The zine concludes with a small text of retractions to form a new message of the inevitable uncertainty of coming and going.
  Geography; Literature; Metaphor in literature; San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.); Maps (documents).
- [untitled], 2012 December 14; UP UGAT (Box 1, Folder 2)
  The stories and poems in the zine feature literal wars people have to fight during the holiday, as well as the struggle of people to pay bills or provide for their families.
  economics; Literature; Christmas; Politics
- [untitled], 2015 January; Farjado, Maria Ana; The Cabinet (Box 1, Folder 3)
  The zine, with photocollages, doodles, and poem, is centered around being remembered and longing, which are expressed through the concept of hands and holding on. Though some lines from the poems correlate with the images, some of them appear to not be related.
  Art; Literature
- [untitled], undated; Chernila Comics (Box 1, Folder 4)
  This is an artist dump of various sketches, doodles, poems, short stories, photographs, and collages. The short stories are written around the theme of abandoning nature, in the representation of a pet dog abandoned, the earth recovering from human greed, and an imagined world in the skies.
  Literature; Art; Nature
- [untitled], undated; Aguilar, Francis Miguel L. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  An art zine by a musician who realizes that every craft will not be executed perfectly after the first try. He decides to paint, for fun, and ends up enjoying the process even if the results wasn't what he expected. The paintings in the zine are inspired by elements from the grunge and classical rock music scene, including long hair and guitars.
  Art; Paintings (visual works).
- #PinkForever, undated; Principe, Allie; The Four-Eyed Wonder (Box 1, Folder 6)
  #PINKFOREVER is a photozine that connects various pantone pink colors with matching photos. Images in the photozine include bridges, buildings, vending machines, furniture and accessories in various shades of pink.
  Pink; Art; Architecture
- +/-, 2017; Majora, Labyu; Ty (Box 1, Folder 7)
  This is a collage styled zine printed in black ink on yellow paper. It is centered around the same situational themes with different points of view. The + collages in this zine were made by Ty, while the - collages were made by Acie.
  collage; Art
- 1, 2013; Cham, Rob (Box 1, Folder 8)
  This is an auto-biographical comic about Rob Cham's journey to becoming a comic artist.
  comics; Autobiography; School Life; Art
- 26%, 2016 December; Delacruz, Vianca; Basilla, Saturnino (Box 1, Folder 9)
  26% by Vianca Delacruz is a zine that was published by Saturnino Basilla in Manila, Philippines. This zine centers on drawings, collages and photographs.
  Traditional Art; Art
- 40 Drawings With Words, 2013; Maria, Apol Sta (Box 1, Folder 10)
  This zine is covered in a textured orange cardstock with green pages inside. It is illustrated with accompanying text.
  Art
- Aaaaaaaaah Trapik, undated; Lutero, Jasmine; Wombatrai (Box 1, Folder 15)
  A collage zine about traffic in Manila, Philippines.
  Epifanio de los Santos Avenue (Manila, Philippines); Traffic; Transportation
- The Abandoned Stage, undated; Dy Recidoro, Zeny May (Box 8, Folder 4)
  The zine contains photos of trees, windows from the inside, plants, the sky, and more. Each photo takes up about a third of each page, execpt for the middle spread, which holds a photo of a tree from inside the house, and through the window. a window with big panes.
  Photography; Art
- Adelaine, 2014; De Gala, Ched (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Adelaine is a short graphic novel with text that tells of the narrator's complicated relationship with his daughter, Adelaine. The cover is yellow with an orang spine while the story is in black and white.
  Family; Art; Literature
- Adobo Man, undated (Box 10, Folder 39)
- Adolescent, 2014; Cesario, Joanne; Bacabac, Michelle (Box 1, Folder 17)
  A short zine with a comic about quitting cigaretes, remembering smells, forgetting details but remembering intimate ones over time.
  Memories; Cigarettes; Art
- Adulting, 2017; Sycip, Ynah; Chernila Comics (Box 1, Folder 18)
  This zine is broken up into two sections: "Surreal" and "Some Final Notions on Adulthood." It is in black and white with the cover printed in color on laminated paper.
  Depression; Art; economics; psychology
- The Adventures of Team Pom: Squid Happens, 2017; Roxas, Isabel; Little Big Time Press (Box 8, Folder 5)
  This is a short comic, printed in two colors on risograph, is by a Brooklyn-based Filipina artist who employs a minimalist art style. It is about three, very different young girls brought together by their love of a show called Diving Divas, who make up a synchronized swimming team named Team Pom.
  Synchronized swimming; Giant Squids; Art
- Again and Again, undated; Gemora, Yanna (Box 1, Folder 19)
  This short comic is about a young boy and girl who constantly clash with each other. After a fight, the boy gets a visit from his future self who advises him to talk to the girl. The boy is suspicious of the advise, but helps out the girl shortly after she is caught in a downpour with a broken umbrella.
  Widow; Time Travel; Science
- Agency Hits Redux, 2017; Bangalan, Glerren; Lahathala Micro Press (Box 1, Folder 20)
  A script for a play that was written for the event Deus Sex Machina, a live comedy erotica live-reading show in Manila. In this script, four women in an agency are assigned to collect ingredients for a new product.
  Chapbook; Erotica.; Literature
- Ah, OK, 2016 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Alaala At Sampaguita, 2013; Genson, Irene; Balita, Nino (Box 1, Folder 21)
  A self-published graphic novel tells the story of Kokoy, an orphan who used his love for his friend, Clara to encourage himself to acheive his life goals in order to gain a relationship with her.
  Sampaguita; Poverty; Oprhans; Philosophy
- Alak: Extra Strong Feelings, 2017; Tango, A. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  A short folded zine about strong pangs of heartache and the attempt to dull it down with alcohol.
  Alcohol Abuse; Breaking Up; psychology; Health
- Alternate Destinations, 2017; De Gala, Ched (Box 1, Folder 23)
  A zine bound together by a book ring, each page split for images and words. It is about the dynamic progression of a relationship of sharing comfort and doubt.
  Romance; Geography
- Always Awake, undated; Wombatrai (Box 1, Folder 24)
  This zine is about complicated feelings of becoming an adult and the uncertainty that comes with decision making.
  Mental Health; Anxiety; Insomnia; Health; psychology
- Anathema (On Notes On Things We Hate), 2016; Santos, Maria Criselda R. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  This zine consists of poems based on different things the writer hates. Some of the notes are accompanied by simple, black, inky sketches. The cover is of a person sitting with a cup of coffee.
  Poetry; Literature
- Andrea And Other Paranoia, 2017; Peroz, Merl (Box 1, Folder 26)
  The cover is black with a purple portrait outline of a woman. This is a series of entries that tells the story of a woman's fears of being abandoned by her husband, the perspective of a young mistress, passage about the drug wars, and the feelings of love, loss and acceptance.
  Paranoia; Adultery; Drug War; War on Drugs; psychology
- Ang Abakada Ng Tunay Na Pag-Ibig, 2017; Vee, Brian (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Abakada ng Tunay na Pagibig is a poem that goes through the Abakada alphabet, or the indigenized version of the Latin alphabet, to convey Brian Vee's love for his girlfriend. This poem was originally created for spoken word before becoming a zine. The zine has minimalist illustrations that compliment the story.
  Spoken Word Poem; Literature; economics
- Ang Alamat Ng Chismis, 2014; Nada, Marcushiro; National Gulaman Authority (Box 1, Folder 28)
  A comedic take on how the word "Chismis" (or gossip) came to be.
  Gossip; Language; Folklore
- Ang Dambuhala at Ang Dinapurak, 2016; Pilares, Christian Ray; Lira, Librong (Box 1, Folder 29)
  This is a compilation of poems from the perspective of workers from factories and call centers. In these poems, the extent that workers have to go to in order to keep their jobs is reflected.
  Union Organizing; Labor unions; Workers; Factory Workers; Call Centers; Literature; Politics; Business
- Ang Hardin Ni Neneng, 2017; De Guzman, Denice; Deus Sex Machina (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Ang Hardin Ni Nene was originally written for the very first Deus Sex Machina, Metro Manila's comedic erotica live reading show. This story about sex references the Filipino folklore song, "bahay kubo," and is paired with illustrations of the vegetables mentioned in that song to appear as an innocent zine for non-Filipino readers.
  Parody; Comedic Erotica; Sexuality; Sex Positivity; Language; Literature
- Ang Lakarang Baliw, 2017; Fernandez, Ica (Box 1, Folder 31)
  The drawings in this zine are inspired by the Major Arcana tarot deck and represent historic, cultural, or political icons from the Philippines. The images and words are translated into Filipino.
  Major Arcana; Tarot; Art; Culture; Folklore; History
- Ang Roommate Kong Aswang, undated; Aquino, Ardie; Ardie Aquino Comics (Box 1, Folder 32)
  A humorous short zine about a boy finding out that his roommate is an aswang (a shapeshifting monster).
  Aswang; Folklore
- Ang Una Kong Pag-gawa ng Komix, undated; Fabo; No. 24 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Fabo's story of how he approached and created his very first comic.
  comics; Art
- ang/gulo, 2014; Malabad, Rizalino Noble; Magpies Press (Box 1, Folder 34)
  These zines by Rizalino Noble Malabad were published by Magpies Press in University of the Philippines Los Baños. In this collection are the zines ang/lou 1: politics and ang/lou: teorya. They are written in English and Filipino.
  Immigration; Corruption; Politics; Revolution; Working Class; History; Culture; economics; Philosophy; Literature; Colonization
  - 1: politics: for we know and cannot unknow / 2: identity: not being at home (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 3: teorya: usaping burgis (Box 1, Folder 34)
- The Astronaut, 2017; Bisuña, Beatrice (Box 8, Folder 6)
  The Astronaut is a worldless comic about a girl who wears an astronaut suit to leave her house.
  Mental Health; Anxiety; Astronauts; Art; psychology
- Baby Love: Understanding Bestiality & Zoophilia, 2014; Dimaranan, Janine; Acuña, Tilde (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Baby Love is a zine that probes a conversation around bestiality and zoophilia. There are references to religious stories and mythology to provide context to the phenomena. This zine is written in English and features doodles over screencaps, pages with religious stories, and pages with definitions of human/animal figures and deities from different religions and cultures.
  Bestiality; Sexuality; Anthropology; psychology; Religion
- Baguio City, undated; Emen; Batocabe, Abbey (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Doodles on newspapers from Baguio City.
  Baguio (Philippines); Tourism; Art; Business
- Bagyo, 2013 December; UP UGAT (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Bagyo is a compilation of poems and stories by students of the University of the Philippines.
  Typhoons; Corruption; economics; Literature; Politics; Education
- Bakas, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Bakemono High, 2013; Or, Elbert (Box 2, Folder 4)
  "Bakemono" is the Japanese word for monster. The comic follows Max, a vampire and the son of the high school's principal, as he anxiously faces his first day at school, and makes new friends.
  High School Life; Monsters; Art; Education
- Bakit Nga Ba?, undated; Midnight Collective (Box 2, Folder 5)
  A compilation of responses from the prompt, "Bakit Nga Ba__?" This prompt, which translates to "Why is it that__," or simply, "Why __?" urged a general audience to submit prompts by filling in the blank. Various writers from the Midnight Collective answered the questions through short stories or poems. The cover is upside down.
  Prompts; Literature
- A Balut Ate My Luois Vuitton, 2013; Maria, Apol Sta (Box 1, Folder 11)
  This is a short comic about a grandma telling her impatient grandson how a balut ate her Louis Vuitton bag when she came back to the Philippines from being an OFW (overseas Filipino worker).
  Balut; Overseas Filipino Workers; Anthropology
- Bangon Luna, undated (Box 10, Folder 42)
- Banyo Chronicles, 2017; White Wall Poetry (Box 2, Folder 6)
  A series of poems that discuss uncomfortable thoughts and feelings.
  Sexuality; Mental Health; Feminism; Abuse; Politics; psychology; Literature; Health
- 1 Beg Komiks a Project Bayani Imprint, undated (Box 10, Folder 31)
- 2 Beg Komiks a Project Bayani Imprint, undated (Box 10, Folder 32)
- 3 Beg Komiks a Project Bayani Imprint, undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
- Bert Certificate, undated; Alvarez, Fran (Box 2, Folder 7)
  A fold out zine that features a water color painting for each day of the week. Once the zine is folded out, the message "Buhay is Life," which is translates to "Life is Life" is shown.
  Watercolors; Art
- Bigote at Balbos, undated (Box 10, Folder 43)
- Bird Ritual, 2017; Afable, Ramon (Box 2, Folder 8)
  A zine that uses different characters and languages, including English, Arabic, and Cyrillic. It contains sketches of bird diagrams, photographs, recipes and more.
  Birds; Obelisk; Art; Language
- Birth. Nature. Something, 2017; Luistro, Mikki (Box 2, Folder 9)
  This is a photozine with 28 black and white photos.
  Photography; Photozine; Art
- The Black Book Trilogy, 2017; Black, Marius; Kuro Saku (Box 8, Folder 7)
  Three stories about relationships that are semi-autobiographical. Each zine tells the story of a teenage girl and her boyfriend. Themes include heartache, jealousy and depression.
  Death; Suicide; Self-mutilation; psychology
  - The Scars on his Wrists (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - The Black Rose (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Someone Else's Life (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Black Feathers Of An Adarna, undated; Lapuz, Vincent; Ciriaco, Gian; Chemical Comics (Box 2, Folder 10)
  A superhero comic.
  Superheroes; Violence
- Bloom, 2017; Chocnut-san (Box 2, Folder 11)
  This zine uses flowers to illustrate different stages of love and life.
  Flowers; Art
- BLUE, 2013; Sim, Bru; Electrolychee (Box 2, Folder 12)
  A colorful, mini-fold out zine about someone going into a woman's house who recently passed away and reflecting on everything she left behind.
- Blue House, undated; Dagal, Camz (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Death; Art; psychology
- A book for suny days: Almond milk and sea salt scrub, undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
- BOSO: A Peep in Pinoy Bomba Komiks, 2017 December; Basilla, Saturnino (Box 2, Folder 14)
  In the Philippines, Bomba Komiks is the general term applied to adult-oriented comics that contain graphic nudity and sexual themes. This zine was prefaced with the question, why read pornography? Saturnino Basilla aims to reclaim pornography, where people's most repressed feelings, experiences, feelings about those experiences, and experiences about those feelings can be reflected. These comics are not to be seen as pornographic content only, but as a means of resistance against censorship.
  comics; Sexuality; Censorship; Feminism; Sex Positivity; Anthropology; Art; Culture; History; psychology; Politics
- Break Up, 2013; Cham, Rob (Box 2, Folder 15)
  This comic documented Rob's emotional journey as he went through his first break up.
  Romance; Breaking Up; Art; psychology
- Buhos, 2017; Zapanta, Ruen; Khakiout (Box 2, Folder 16)
  A wordless comic about an office girl who wants nothing more than to get a cup of hot chocolate milk.
  Work Life; Rain; Art; psychology
- Bunshin, 2017 June; Black, Marius (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Marius Black's alter ego's poetry. The light blue book has Filipino poems about pining and sex, while the light pink ones features poems around the same themes, but are in English.
  Poetry; Sexuality; Literature
  - Light Blue (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Light Pink (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Burn Baby Burn, undated; Aquino, Ardie (Box 2, Folder 18)
  A short comic about a man who runs into repeated misfortune.
  Fire; Suicide; psychology
- Buti pa ang Cupcake ma fillings, undated (Box 10, Folder 44)
- BUXXXOM GRIND, 2014 July; Gadia, Dina; Basilla, Saturnino (Box 2, Folder 19)
  BUXXXOM GRIND is a zine created by Dina Gadia, and published in Manila, Philippines. It contains collaged images of women that are printed on pink paper and in black ink.
  Photography; collage; Feminism; Sexuality; Art; Culture
- Byaheng Pinoy, 2013; Casanova, Raphael Cezar; Dy, Freya; Neko, Yume; Dr. RaCe's Publishing House (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Byaheng Pinoy (Pinoy Travels) is a Taglish oneshot comic that tells the everyday experiences of a commuter in Manila through slapstick humor.
  Manila (Philippines); Humor; Social life and customs; Jeepney; Commute; Culture; Geography; Transportation
- Cact Luv, undated; Felipe, Keeshia (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Cact Luv is a zine by Keeshia Felipe or "Kita" filled with drawings that mix the elements of cute and tough. Most of the illustrations include doodles of young girls, cute skulls, fashion, and daily activities like thrift shopping and eating french fries.
  Ukay-Ukay; Fashion; Art; Culture
- Catnip (Ang Masusing Pagmamasid), 2016 (Box 10, Folder 37)
- The Census of San Malo, 2017; Aguinaldo, Dennis; Valentino, Kevin Ray; Drifting Vimana (Box 8, Folder 8)
  The Census of San Malo is a comic inspired by a throwaway line about "certain tribes" in the Philippines from H.P. Lovecraft's "Call of the Cthulhu." It is about a Katipunero who investigates whether forced labor is happening in San Malo, which only has 28 families with no more than two children each.
  Saint Malo (La.); Supernatural; Katipunero; Cult; Geography; Race; Religion
- Cheesyfit, 2014-2017; Casipit, Mel (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Cheesyfit is an illustrated joke book containing funny pick-up lines in English and Tagalog.
  Joke Book; Romance; Humor; Pickup Lines; Culture; Language; Technology
  - Cheesyfit, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Cheesyfit 2, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Cheesyfit 3, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Cheesyfit 4, 2016 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Cheesyfit 5, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Chernila 7 1/2: The Flavor Issue, 2016; Sycip, Ynah; Chernila Comics (Box 2, Folder 23)
  The Flavor Issue of Chernila is a compilation of short comics that are about relationships, friendships, and childhood imagination.
  Food; psychology
- The Chibi Collection of 2 Sentence Horror Stories!, undated; Llanto, Chuck; Eventual Empire (Box 8, Folder 9)
  A zine with a compilation of 2-sentence horror stories, along with a matching chibi (Japanese slang for short or little) drawing for each one.
  Horror; Chibi; Art
- The Chlorine Atom Girl, 2013; Puangco, Wina; MoarBooks (Box 8, Folder 10)
  A collection of three short stories of a girl recalling her past relationship through a series of questions, to a girl coined as chlorine atom girl because she dissolves from the lives of men quickly, and to a nonlinear story that shows how a man got to the point of jumping off a building.
  Mental Health; Literature
- CHOPSUEY 2014, Handick, Bernard; Sergio, Brian; Longboy, Fade; Mazinger Zine; Everywhere We Shoot (Box 2, Folder 24)
  The zine contains a compilation of alternative photography by different artists that contains sensual, sexual, and mundane images.
  Manila (Philippines); Photography; Sexuality; Art
- The Chronicles of Chin Chin and Timmy, 2017; Sia, Jacqueline J.; 8Letters (Box 8, Folder 11)
  A compilation of poems, short stories, and diary entrees that record the course and progression of an unrequited love from a mother to a jeepney driver she runs into, and befriends.
  Hugot; Jeepney; Unrequited Love; Literature; Transportation
- Chuck Lllanto #1, undated; Llanto, Chuck (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Includes original art and fan art by Chuck Llanto. The illustrations and doodles are centered around single-person characters, who are portrayed in each page in full color.
- Club., 2017 December; Swann, Hope (Box 2, Folder 26)
  The suicide of Lee, or Julia Louise Buencamino, a 15-year old actor in the Philippines left a great period of grief for her loved ones. "Club." is a what Hope Swann dubs the group of people that were listed in Lee's suicide letter. This zine sorts out the feelings of guilt and grief about the suicide, and walks through the events that happened afterwards.
  Suicide; Mental Health; Grief; Mourning; Health; psychology; Buencamino, Julia Louise